Guide to the George Breitman Papers TAM.169
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
George Breitman Papers
1919-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Breitman, George
Breitman, Dorothy
TAM.169
38 Linear Feet in 33 manuscript boxes, 5 record cartons, 4 cassette boxes and one folder.
122 audiocassettes
38 sound tape reels
George Breitman (1916-1986) was a Trotskyist and a founding member of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP). He edited The Militant newspaper and served in World War II. In the 1960s, Breitman assumed responsibility for the SWP's Pathfinder Press, edited Writings of Leon Trotsky, 1929-1940, and wrote Malcolm X Speaks (1965). The George Breitman Papers contain personal files, correspondence, files of the Socialist Workers Party and other socialist organizations, written works, audio recordings of events and lectures, and photographs. The materials portay Breitman's life and work, including scholarly work and activism relating to U.S. socialism, Trotskyism, Malcolm X, and the Black Power and Civil Rights movements.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dorothy Breitman in 1995. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1992.006, 1992.010, 1992.013, and NPA.2001.024. A second accession was donated in 1997.
Appraisal
In November 2024, 8 audiocassettes with duplicative content were deaccessioned. In March 2025, 3 audiocassettes and 1 quarter inch audio reel with duplicative content were deaccessioned.
Arrangement
The Papers are organized into seven series, with two further divided into subseries and subsubseries:
Series I: Biographical Materials
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Political Organizations and Activities
Subseries A: Socialist Workers Party
Subsubseries 1. General records and activities
Subsubseries 2. Educational Activities
Subsubseries 3. Publications Committee
Subsubseries 4. FBI Files - General
Subsubseries 5. FBI Files - James Kutcher
Subseries B. Other Trotskyist Organizations
Series IV: Writings, Lectures, and Interviews
Subseries A: Writings, General
Subseries B: Socialist Workers Party History
Subseries C: Malcolm X
Subseries D: African Americans
Subseries E: James P. Cannon
Subseries F: Leon Trotsky
Subseries G: Carl Skoglund
Subseries H: Alan Wald correspondence
Subseries I: Louis Sinclair Correspondence
Subseries J: General Correspondence
Subseries K: Writings by Others
Series V: Lists and Indexes
Series VI: Addendum
Series VII: Photographs
Biographical Note
George Breitman (1916-1986) was born in a working-class neighborhood of Newark, New Jersey in 1916. After graduating from high school, Breitman found work in the Civilian Conservation Corps and later in the Works Progress Administration. By 1935, he had joined the Trotskyist movement as a member of the Spartacus Youth League and then as a member of the Workers Party. He also joined the New Jersey branch of the Workers Alliance of America, an organization that fought for relief during the Great Depression.
The Socialist Workers Party (SWP) was founded in 1938 and Breitman was a founding member. In 1941, Breitman assumed editorship of the SWP's weekly newspaper, The Militant. Drafted and sent to France in 1943, he contacted a number of European Trotskyists and helped rebuild the war-battered Fourth International. After his return to the United States, he became editor of The Militant in the late 1940s and early 1950s. From the mid-1950s to the late 1960s, Breitman worked as a proofreader and was a member of the International Typographical Union. In this period he was also the leader of the Detroit branch of the SWP. With his wife Dorothea, and Frank and Sarah Lovell, he initiated the Friday Night Socialist Forum (later called the Militant Forum), a weekly series that attracted a broad range of activists from the labor, left, student and African American movements. Through this period, Breitman used several pseudonyms, including Albert Parker, Philip Blake, Anthony Massini, John F. Petrone, and Chester Hofla. Returning to New York in the late 1960s, Breitman assumed responsibility for the SWP's Pathfinder Press. He edited the 14-volume Writings of Leon Trotsky, 1929-1940 (1969-1979), worked on various collections of the writings of James P. Cannon, and edited Malcolm X Speaks (1965). In the course of these activities Breitman corresponded with scholars and added to his collection of Trotskyist documentation.
In the late 1970s Breitman opposed the growing trend among the SWP leadership toward what he viewed as a politics focused on Castro's leadership of the Cuban Communist Party. Among the hundreds expelled from the SWP in the early 1980s, he played a leading role in establishing the Fourth Internationalist Tendency, which sought to unify U.S. supporters of the Fourth International. Breitman died of a heart attack in 1986.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Scope and Content Note
The George Breitman Papers (1919-1989) contain personal files, correspondence, files of the Socialist Workers Party and other political organizations, published and unpublished writings, audio recordings of events and lectures, and photographs. The materials portay Breitman's life and work, including scholarly work and activism relating to socialist movements, Trotskyism, Malcolm X, and the Black Power and Civil Rights movements.
The personal files in this collection include documents related to Breitman's service in World War II and his involvement in the Workers Alliance of America, an autobiographical sketch, and recordings of memorial services.
A significant amount of the materials in the collection relate to Breitman's involvement and later expulsion from the Socialist Workers Party, including correspondence, committee meeting minutes, proceedings, reports, memos, pre-convention and other discussion, FOIA files, position papers, and materials documenting the activities of the organization. Breitman was also affiliated with the Fourth Internationalist Tendency and the Communist League of America. Audio recordings portray meeting proceedings as well as lectures on the history of the Socialist Workers Party and other organizations.
Breitman wrote and edited articles and manuscripts on topics such as Malcolm X, the Black Power and Civil Rights movements, socialist movements, and Trotskyism. This collection includes written correspondence with scholars and activists, published and unpublished typescripts, transcripts of speeches and lectures, lists of articles in Trotskyist periodicals, and audio recordings of lectures, interviews, and events. Written work and audio recordings in this collection document the activism of Malcolm X, the Black Liberation movements of the late 1950s - early 1970s, and Trotskyism.
Communism -- United States.; Civil rights and socialism -- United States; African American communists; Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; Typescripts; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorandums.; Socialism -- United States.; Proceedings.; Government records; Clippings (information artifacts); Trotskyism -- United States.; Workers Party (1940-1949); X, Malcolm, 1925-1965; Fourth International; Fourth Internationalist Tendency (Group); Breitman, George; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999.; Healy, G.; Kutcher, James; Dobbs, Farrell; Cannon, James Patrick, 1890-1974; Lovell, Frank; Cleaver, Eldridge, 1935-1998; Merit Publishers; Broue, Pierre; Pathfinder Press; Barnes, Betsy; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974; Hansen, Joseph; Guerin, Daniel, 1904-; Socialist Party (U.S.); Socialist Workers Party; Worthy, William, 1921-; Weiss, Murry; Redgrave, Vanessa, 1937-; Williams, Robert; Shaw, Ed; Breitman, Dorothy
- Series I. Biographical Materials, 1935-1986; 1.5 Linear Feet in 3 containers
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I. Biographical Materials contains an autobiographical sketch, memorabilia from the 1930s and from Breitman's WWII military service, and materials pertaining to several memorial services.
  - Civilian Conservation Corps, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Workers Alliance - Arrest of Breitman, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Workers Relief and WPA Union membership card, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - World War II - Army experiences, 1943-circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Croix de Guerre avec etoile de bronze, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Autobiographical Sketch, 3 pages, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Larry Stewart Memorial, December 16, 1984; cuid42880 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0130)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Preservation Note: The audio quality varies throughout.
  - Weissman Memorial, April 11, 1985; cuid42879 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0127)
    Preservation Note: The tape hubs were replaced.
  - Correspondence: U.S. Department of Justice (FOIA), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Broadside: Breitman Memorial Service - Los Angeles, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George Breitman Memorial, June 1, 1986; cuid42882 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0132)
  - Curtiss Memorial, Undated; cuid42897 (Box 72, Audiocassette 169_0148)
    Scope and Contents
    In celebration of the life of Lillian M. Curtiss (1911-1985)
    Preservation Note: Side 1 has poor audio quality, with pitch variation and flutter apparent during music intros/outros, and an electronic hum.
- Series II. Correspondence, 1935-1986; 11 Linear Feet 11 containers
  Series II. Correspondence contains the bulk of Breitman's correspondence, and is principally concerned with his political activities as a member of the Socialist Workers Party and later the Fourth Internationalist Tendency. Correspondents include: Betsy Barnes, Pierre Broue, James Cannon, Eldridge Cleaver, Farrell Dobbs, Al Glotzer, Daniel Guerin, Joseph Hansen, Gerry Healy, James Kutcher, Walter Lippman, Frank Lovell, Vanessa Redgrave, Ed Shaw, Robert Williams, Murry Weiss, William Worthy. There is also some Breitman correspondence in series III, and throughout series IV.
  - Correspondence, 1935-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1954-Nov 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1954-Dec 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1955-Feb 1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Mar 1955-Apr 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, May 1955-Jul 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1955-Dec 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1956-Apr 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, May 1956-Aug 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1956-Dec 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1957-Sep 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1957-Dec 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1958-Apr 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 1958-Dec 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1959-Mar 1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1959-Jun 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1959-Nov 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1960-Jun 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1960-Nov 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Dec 1960-Dec 1960 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1961-Aug 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1961-Dec 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1962-Jul 1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1962-Dec 1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1963-Mar 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1963-May 1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1963-Dec 1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1964-Mar 1964 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1964-Jun 1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1964-Dec 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1965-Mar 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1965-May 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1965-Jul 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1965-Oct 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1965-Dec 1965 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1966-Jun 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1966-Aug 1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1966-Dec 1966 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1967-Apr 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, May 1967-Oct 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1967-Dec 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1968-Jul 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1968-Nov 1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1968-Dec 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1969-May 1969 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, May 1969-Dec 1969 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1970-Jun 1970 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1970-Dec 1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1971-Jun 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1971-Oct 1971 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1971-Dec 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1972-Jul 1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1972-Dec 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1973-Jun 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1973-Dec 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1974-Jun 1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1974-Dec 1974 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1975-Jun 1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1973-May 1976 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1976-Dec 1976 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1977-Jun 1977 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1977-Sep 1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1977-Dec 1977 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1978-May 1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1978-Dec 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1979-Jun 1979 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1979-Oct 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1979-Dec 1979 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1980-Apr 1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, May 1980-Sep 1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1980-Dec 1980 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1981-Mar 1981 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1981-Jul 1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1981-Sep 1981 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1981-Dec 1981 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Le Blanc, Paul, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 4.5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1982-Mar 1982 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1982-Jul 1982 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1982-Dec 1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1983-Feb 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Mar 1983-Jun 1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1983-Dec 1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1984-Apr 1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, May 1984-Jun 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1984-Aug 1984 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1984-Oct 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1984-Dec 1984 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1985-Feb 1985 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Mar 1985-May 1985 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1985-Jul 1985 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Aug 1985-Oct 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Nov 1985-Dec 1985 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1985-Nov 1985 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - Le Blanc, Paul, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 6.5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1986-Mar 1986 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1986-Jun 1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Apr 1986 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Series III. Political Organizations and Activities, 1930-1986; 34 Linear Feet in 34 containers
  Series III. Political Organizations and Activities contains committee, club, and branch meeting minutes, convention proceedings, discussion and position papers, reports and memos, correspondence of Breitman and others, and FBI files. There is coverage of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) from its inception, although the greatest concentration of material is from the 1950s-60s and from 1982-85, the period leading up to, and immediately after Breitman's expulsion. For the Newark and Detroit clubs, there are minutes, typescripts of Breitman's talks and lectures, and documentation of Breitman's several runs for public office. Many files deal with views of the USSR, the Shachtman/Workers Party split, Pabloism, and the Cochranite split, including: "Toward Brass Tacks," by James Burnham, 1939; W. Roark (Trotsky) Letters re Opposition, 1940; "Shamefaced Defensism," by Dwight MacDonald, 1940; "Russian Theses," by E. R. Frank, 1948-49; "Pabloism revisited" by Peng, 1955; and an account of a (confidential) interview with Louis Adamic, 1950. Significant files on African Americans include resolutions written by R. Kirk, 1953; "Why white radicals are incapable of understanding black nationalism," by R. Vernon, 1963; the SWP Black Fraction, 1967-68; and various Breitman lectures and resolutions. Files from the late 1970s - early 1980s document Breitman's political differences with the SWP line, his expulsion and the aftermath. The James Kutcher FBI files pertain to the case of this legless World War II veteran who in 1948 was dismissed from his job as a Veterans Administration clerk in Newark, NJ because of his SWP membership. The other FBI files document the Detroit Friday Night Forum, and the case of the SWP vs the U.S. Attorney General (1980s).
  This series is arranged into two subseries:
  Subseries A: Socialist Workers Party
  Subsubseries 1. General records and activities
  Subsubseries 2. Educational Activities
  Subsubseries 3. Publications Committee
  Subsubseries 4. FBI Files - General
  Subsubseries 5. FBI Files - James Kutcher
  Subseries B. Other Trotskyist Organizations
  - Subseries A: Socialist Workers Party, 1930-1986
    Subsubseries arranged chronologically.
    - Subsubseries 1 -- General, 1930-1985
      - Brochure for anti-fascist rally in Yiddish, 1930s (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Convention (Founding), 1937-1938 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Melos Most ('Left-Wing Correspondence' / 'Appeal Left Wing'), 1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Minnesota farmer-Labor Party, draft thesis on, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - National Committee, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Nazi pogroms, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Political Committee, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - "Workers Voice" (Socialist Workers Party Lenin Branch, Newark District), 1938 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - American fund for political prisoners, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Anti-war fund campaign, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Burnham, James - "Toward brass tacks", 1939 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Constitution (as amended by 2nd convention), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Convention (2nd, New York City), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - French Trotskyism, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Minutes of the Club Executive, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - National Committee, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Negro work, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Political Committee, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - Resolutions, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - Russian question, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - San Francisco Bay Area majority - statement of organization, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - Wright, John G. "Ideological captives of the bourgeoisie", 1939 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - Breitman U.S. Senate campaign/Assembly campaign, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Constitution (amended at 3rd convention), 1940 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Convention (third), 1940 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Convention (fourth), Dec 1940 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Majority documents, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - National Committee, Sep 1940 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Opposition documents - anonymous, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Opposition documents - authored, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Opposition documents - "Shamefaced defensism" by Dwight MacDonald, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Trotsky memorial meeting - Chicago, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Roark, W. (Trotsky) letters re Opposition, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Breitman campaign for Newark City Commission, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Campaign fliers for Newark City Commission and US Senate, 1940-1941 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS004)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - National Committee meeting, October 10-12, 1941; minutes, draft of revised declaration of principles (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Breitman campaign for U.S. Senate (New Jersey), 1941 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - Control Commission re: comrade Dennis (Flint, MI auto worker), May 1942 (Box 14, Folder 18)
      - Convention (10th) - New York City, Oct 1942 (Box 14, Folder 19)
      - Dobbs, Farrell (Labor Secretary) - letters to activists, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 20)
      - Goldman (?) untitled statement, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 21)
      - "Instructive experience in Negro work", Dec 1942 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Morrow, Felix: "From minutes of the National Education Department, 12/26/42" - includes 4 pp memo, "For workers' control of...shipment of...munitions to the...Soviet Union", 1942 (Box 14, Folder 23)
      - "The Jews and the Revolutionary Party", circa 1944 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Documents, 1945-1947 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Weiss, Murry "Notes for a discussion on the Negro Question", 1945 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Club Executive - minutes, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Electoral campaign, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Morrow, Felix: Against the Political Committee's "theses" on the American revolution and "tasks of the Socialist Workers Party in the present political situation", 1946 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Documents, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Breitman: Electoral analysis, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Breitman: Electoral campaigns, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Breitman: Wallace campaign writings, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Frank, E.R. (i.e., Bert Cochran): "...Russian theses", 1948 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Negro Question, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Negro work, report on (Breitman), 1948 (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - San Diego, San Francisco branches, circa 1948 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      - Frank, E.R. "...on the evolution of buffer countries", 1949 (Box 15, Folder 17)
      - "Account of an interview with Louis Adamic", 8 pages, April 23rd [confidential - for NC members & alternates only], 1950 (Box 15, Folder 18)
      - Club Executive - minutes, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 19)
      - Electoral campaigns, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 20)
      - Political "Statements," "Comments," by Socialist Workers Party activists, leaders, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 21)
      - Club Executive minutes, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 22)
      - Electoral campaigns, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 23)
      - Friday Night Socialist forum - Newark, New Jersey, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 24)
      - Marxist Labor School: "The first American revolution" - lectures outlines, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 25)
      - Political statements, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 26)
      - Documents (includes December report on the 12th NC plenum, 9 pages), 1952 (Box 15, Folder 27)
      - Breitman - talk re death of Harry T. Moore (African-American), 1952 (Box 15, Folder 28)